A Guide to the Papers of John Hooe and Other Families from Prince William & Surrounding Counties ca. 1685-1855
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Hooe and Other Families from Prince William & and Surrounding Counties ca. 1685-1855
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11357
ca. 150 items (1 Hollinger box)
The papers of John Hooe, Jr. of Prince William County, Virginia, who served as a delegate to the Virginia House of Delegates, consists of ca. 150 items (1 Hollinger box) ca. 1685-1855, and contains correspondence, legal & financial papers, and three bound volumes, including two account ledgers from Hooe's blacksmith shop. The earlier blacksmith account ledger, ca. 1812-1832, also contains copies of wills, "A List of Voters in Prince William County April 5, 1819," farm records concerning wheat, corn, and hogs, mentioning Bradley Farm, Graham Park, Yorkshire Farm, Locust Grove, Hansfarm, Cancer Farm, and Bloom's Grove, miscellaneous recipes and notes, and a slave hire for John from Mrs. Susannah F. Graham (1831 Jan 7). The farm ledger, 1842-1845, belonging to [John Hooe, Jr.?] also has accounts for the Toll Road [Hunting Creek Turnpike ?]. Other families represented in the collection include the Beverley, Blackburne, Gaines, Mason, Reid, Wickcliffe, Kincheloe and Foote, from Prince William, Stafford County, Fairfax, Fredericksburg, and surrounding counties.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Jerry N. Showalter, Bookseller, Rare Books and Autographs, Ivy, Virginia, on November 4, 1997.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of John Hooe, Jr. of Prince William County, Virginia, who served as a delegate to the Virginia House of Delegates, consists of ca. 150 items (1 Hollinger box) ca. 1685-1855, and contains correspondence, legal & financial papers, and three bound volumes, including two account ledgers from Hooe's blacksmith shop. The earlier blacksmith account ledger, ca. 1812-1832, also contains copies of wills, "A List of Voters in Prince William County April 5, 1819," farm records concerning wheat, corn, and hogs, mentioning Bradley Farm, Graham Park, Yorkshire Farm, Locust Grove, Hansfarm, Cancer Farm, and Bloom's Grove, miscellaneous recipes and notes, and a slave hire for John from Mrs. Susannah F. Graham (1831 Jan 7). The farm ledger, 1842-1845, belonging to [John Hooe, Jr.?] also has accounts for the Toll Road [Hunting Creek Turnpike ?].
Other families represented in the collection include the Beverley, Blackburne, Gaines, Mason, Reid, Wickcliffe, Kincheloe and Foote, from Prince William, Stafford County, Fairfax, Fredericksburg, and surrounding counties.
The folder of general correspondence is chiefly concerned with farm business, land deeds and sales, and legal cases. A letter to the sitting judges, 1802 September 17, refers to the completion of the court house at Hay Market, Virginia, for the Fredericksburg District Court, and a draft of a letter, 1849 April 18, discusses a railroad bill in the Virginia House of Delegates.
The folder of the correspondence of Richard Foote, John Gibson, and Philip Harrison is totally concerned with the collection and payment of debts.
The correspondence of John Hooe, Jr., 1819-1845, is also chiefly concerned with business matters, but also includes letters concerning the need for Virginia to support Henry Clay (G. Sweeny, 1828 Oct 29); a letter referring to an attempt to establish a new county to be called Warren County, made from Frederick County and Shenandoah County, which actually took place in 1836 (1833 Dec 12); notification of a Whig barbeque sponsored by the Tippecanoe Club of Occoquan (1840 Jun 26); and Hugh Bernard informing his uncle about his plans to marry into the family of Dr. Hall (1841 Nov 3).
The legal and financial papers of Richard Foote include an account with [John?] Gibson, Jr. (1821); receipts for legal fees paid to the court for Spotsylvania County and Fauquier County (1832-1834); receipt from Basil Gordon (1835); a promissory note to Jacob Weaver (1834); an account of A. Sinclair against the estate of Richard Foote (1834 May 20); and an account of sums paid by H. Foote, as administrator for Richard Foote, who was a trustee on behalf of L.H. Fitzhugh and children (1834 Aug 7 through 1836).
The legal and financial papers of the Hooe family include an order to survey land from John Hooe to John Moffett (1775); a deed of lease and release between George Mason and John Hooe (1777); agreement to sell a crop of wheat from Bernard Hooe, Jr. to James Smith (1801); a survey plat by R.B. Ratcliffe (1804); indenture between Isaac & Mary Davis and Bernard Hooe, Jr. (1807); George Tebbs release to Matthew Gregg (1809); accounts (1813, 1826, 1836); Mutual Assurance Society receipts (1821); copies of the courses of tracts of land owned by James Bland and George Reeves for Bernard Hooe, Jr.(1822); land plat, Hanbrough to Hooe (1823); receipts (1824, 1841, 1844); indenture between William H. & Eliza Thacker Fowle, Margaretta Susanna Hooe, and Thomas P. Hooe (1832); indenture between executors of estate of Alexander Henderson and John Hooe (1833); complaint against John Hooe, Jr. (1843); Hayden vs Hooe (1845); estate of John Hooe, Jr. (1845-1847); Buckner v. Hooe (1847); and two plats of land purchased by John Hooe from John Linton along King?s Creek (undated).
The remaining legal and financial papers include: deeds & indentures between Martin Scarlett, Stafford County, and Edward Barton (1685 Jul 8); Leonard Helms, Stafford County (1726 Jan 25); Thomas Daven and Margaret Evans (1739 May 30); Thomas Davis and William Bird (1740 Jul 22); Harrison Manly and Thomas Hammet (1773 Aug 31); Mary & William Champ, Culpeper County, and Lewis Willis (1779 Sep 7); Arrington Wickliffe to Moses Wickliffe (1799); Cornelius & Dorcus Kincheloe, Fairfax, and Moses Wickcliffe (1801); the will of Edward Barton, Stafford County (1712 Jan 10); particulars concerning the Fairfax land purchased by Governor Lee (1729); bonds between Jacob Gibson and Richard Blackburne (1735 Jul 29); William Waller & Ann Beverley, Spotsylvania County and William Beverley, Essex County ([post 1832] Jun 26); lawsuit of Richard Marshall Scott, trustee of Elisha Janney, vs Samuel Dunlap (1809 Dec 13); boundaries and description of the Pope Castle Land (ca. 1816); documents concerning the estate of Augustus Gains, William Brawner, administrator (ca. 1817-1826); promissory note between Thomas & William Brawner and James Taliaferro, Jr. (1823); land grant to Mark Chilton, Stafford County (copied in 1825); report on the estate of Slighter Smith by B. Hooe, listing slaves John, Nace, and Felicia (1842 Dec 22); property tax book, below Cedar Run (1847 Aug 18); Bloom's Grove tract of land (n.d.); and land grant to Robert Carter for the Bull Run tract (n.d.).
Contents List
- Blacksmith Account Book of John Hooe, Jr., including "A List of Voters in Prince William County," and Farm Records ca. 1812-1832 (Box 1)
- Blacksmith Account Book of John Hooe, Jr. 1832-1838 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1797-1849 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Richard Foote 1829-1833 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of John Hooe, Jr. 1819-1845 (Box 1)
- Farm Ledger, also containing entries for the Toll Road, probably the [Hunting Creek Turnpike?] 1842-1845 (Box 1)
- Ledger & Financial Papers 1685-1855, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Legal & Financial Papers of Richard Foote 1821-1835 (Box 1)
- Legal & Financial Papers of the Hooe Family 1775-1849, n.d. (Box 1)
- Indenture between Joseph Hannis, Essex County, and Robert Beverly, Essex County 1724 May 2 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between William mason, Stafford County, and Ann Mason, widow of Prince William County 1731 Oct 20, 2 documents (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between Jacob Gibson and Richard Blackburne, both of Prince William 1735 June 18, 2 documents (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between William Beverly and Thomas Wood, Orange County, concerning "Octonia" 1737 Oct 8 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between Richard Osborne and Richard Blackburne, Prince William County 1739 Jun 21 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between Nathaniel Russell, Patrick & Mary Trail, Prince William County, and Richard Blackburne, Prince William County 1739 Jul 3 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between James Booth, Richmond, and Daniel Kinchloe, Prince William County 1755 Nov 24 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Extracts of Deeds from James Bland to James I. Dozier, all of Prince William County 1761 Jul 24 & 25 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Letter of James Smith, Eden[?] to David Griffith, New York, concerning the rivalry between Jay and Jones 1761 [n.m.] 20 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between John & Betty Linton, Prince William County, and John Hooe, Prince William County 1772 Dec 4 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between George Mason of South Carolina and Virginia, and John Hooe, Prince William County 1777 May 22 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between Daniel Kinchloe, Fairfax County, and Thomas Bird, Prince William 1784 Aug 2 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between Arrington Wickcliffe and John Hooe, Prince William County 1785 Sep 1 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between Arrington Wickcliffe and John Hooe, Prince William County 1785 Sep 2 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Land Plat of land surveyed by Thomas Nelson, Jr., sold from Hansborough to Hooe 1822 Dec 30 (Oversize OS Box P-22)
- Indenture between Moses & Jane Reeve, Prince William County, and John Hammott, Prince William County 1773 Nov 27 (Othertype OS Tray 17)
- Indenture between John Hall, Loudon County, and James Whaley, Loudoun County 1775 Feb 2 (Othertype OS Tray 17)
- Deed between John Hooe and Charles Wickcliffe, Prince William County, surveyor Cornelius Kinchloe 1779 Aug 4 (Othertype OS Tray 17)
- Indenture between Peter & Anne Frances Hansborough, Jr. and Bernard Hooe, Jr. 1796 Mar 10 (Othertype OS Tray 17)
- Henry Davis and Moses Wickcliffe, Prince William County 1801 Feb 10 (Othertype OS Tray 17)
- Indenture between Isaac & Davis, Muhlenberg County, Kentucky, and Bernard Hooe, Prince William County, Virginia 1809 Jul 10 (Othertype OS Tray 17)